Guide to the Ezra Cornell Papers, 1746-1888
Cornell, Ezra Papers, 1746-1888
- Series I. Correspondence 1746-1878
  - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence
    - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence :: 1848-1850
      - December 1, 1848 - December 13, 1848 (Box 9, Folder 2)
        December 12, 1848. J.J. Speed to Ezra Cornell on the financial resolution of the O'Reilly controversy.
        Detroit; Michigan; Montreal.
        Allen, Oliver E.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Speed, J.J.; O'Reilly, Henry; Smith, F.O.J.; Cornell, E.B.; Cornell, John H.; Wood, M.B.; Wood, O.S.; Morse, Samuel F.B.
      - December 14, 1848 - December 29, 1848 (Box 9, Folder 3)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, disputes concerning western lines, finances, stock subscriptions, proposed lines, construction of lines.
        December 14, 1848. Horace Palmer to Alonzo B. Cornell concerning women, "theatres," and lost love.
        December 18, 1848. Douglass Boardman to Ezra Cornell:
        "The operator at Jefferson was directed by some one to teach no one the art of Telegraphic writing while at Jefferson. Believing this to be against the future interests of the Company I directed him to teach any one all he knew about it and no member of the Company would object."
        December 20, 1848. J.H. McFarland to Ezra Cornell:
        "The New York Albany and Buffalo Line refuse to send coms orginating on our line & addressed to points on that line unless we pay their tariff."
        December 21, 1848. H.C. Gilbert to Ezra Cornell:
        "The language of your letter of the 18th is really astonishing & unreasonable."
        Cleveland; Ithaca; Auburn, N.Y.; Detroit.
        Tillotson, D.T.; Palmer, Horace; Bristol, John S.; Speed, J.J.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Boardman, Douglass; MacFarland, J.H.; Gilbert, H.C.; Cornell, E.B.; Wood, M.L.; Wilson, William Duane; Wood, Otis E.
      - December 31, 1848 - January 7, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 4)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, western lines, stock subscriptions, conflict with O'Reilly's lines, patent rights.
        December 31, 1848. Alonzo B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "I see the cholera is approaching the Lakes on every side, both east and south. It is now in Cincinnatti & all the way up the Miss. now."
        December 31, 1848. Jane Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "Ezra I believe you belong to the "Sons of Temperance" and if so I will inform you that there has been a society organized in Albion called "Daughters of Temperance" and that Phebe and I have joined and like it first rate."
        January 2, 1849. Jane Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "?I have nothing to dress in on that occasion, that is I have no dress that will answer to appear on the stage in. All the young ladies will appear in silk or merino and as I have nothing but a delaine that I have had above a year, I thought that I would write you the circumstances and trust to your generosity in helping me procure one."
        Cleveland; Albion.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cornell, Jane; Allen, Oliver E.; Speed, J.J.
      - January 8, 1849 - January 24, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 5)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, western lines, conflict with O'Reilly's lines, stocks, patent rights; cholera.
        January 17, 1849. J.J. Speed to Ezra Cornell:
        "We must have a line from St. Louis to Fort Independence, and ultimately to the great Commercial Emporium on the Pacific, at the bay of San Francisco. If the 'gold diggins' are what they are cracked up to be, there will be a city at San Francisco of more than one hundred thousand inhabitants in less than ten years, Whitneys RRoad will be built and the telegraph along side of it."
        Detroit; Cleveland.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Speed, J.J.; O'Reilly, Henry; Tillotson, D.T.
      - January 25, 1849 - February 9, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 6)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, western lines, proposed line (Cuba), disputes concerning western lines, O'Reilly's proposed lines; cholera; gold fever.
        January 27, 1849. Alonzo B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "The people are not, in this part of the country, a quarter so much excited about the Cholera as the Gold fever."
        Cornell, E.B.; Wood, O.S.; O'Reilly, Henry; Speed, J.J.; Bristol, John S.; Hoyt, Byron B.; Nutter, J.; Tillotson, D.T.; Cornell, Alonzo B.
      - February 10, 1849 - February 28, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 7)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, new lines, patent rights, western lines, Connecticut & Vermont line; gold fever.
        Massachusetts; New York City; Detroit; Montreal.
        Bristol, John S.; Bulkley, Charles S.; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Tillotson, D.T.; Speed, J.J.; Smith, F.O.J.; Wood, O.S.
      - March 2, 1849 - March 20, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 8)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, western lines, conflict with O'Reilly's lines, new lines, stocks.
        March 10, 15, and 17, 1849. J.J. Speed's experiments and speculations concerning telegraph science.
        Detroit; New York City; Ithaca; Fredonia.
        Bristol, John S.; Smith, F.O.J.; Briggs, Amos; Speed, J.J.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Dunham, J.; Cobb, Emory.
      - March 20, 1849 - March 31, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 9)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, western lines.
        March 28, 1849. J.J. Speed on telegraph technology and Morse's patent.
        Fredonia; Detroit.
        Tillotson, D.T.; Speed, J.J.; Park, J.D.; Cornell, Jane; Pew, W.P.
      - April 2, 1849 - April 18, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 10)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, western lines, conflict with O'Reilly's lines, Erie & Michigan line.
        April 13, 1849. J.J. Speed's experiments and speculations concerning telegraph science.
        April 15, 1849. Jane Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "Mary has left of doctoring with a Botanic Doctor, and is taking Myres Sarsaparilla Dandelion & Wild-cherry extract?"
        Speed, J.J.; Cornell, Jane; Briggs, Amos; Cornell, E.S.; Cornell, John H.
      - April 19, 1849 - April 30, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 11)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, western lines, conflict with O'Reilly's lines, new lines.
        April 23, 1849. J.J. Speed to Ezra Cornell:
        "O'Reilly now refuses to take coms from us to go South from any place where they have an office. Shall we refuse to take coms from them going West? If anything is left to my discretion I give you notice now, that my propensities are decidedly for war."
        Also, April 23, 27, 28, 30, 1849: J.J. Speed's speculations concerning telegraph science.
        April 29, 1849. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell on temperance.
        McFarland, J.H.; Wood, O.S.; Speed, J.J.
      - May 1, 1849 - May 18, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 12)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, western lines, rates, conflict with O'Reilly's lines, Canadian lines.
        May 6, 1849. J.J. Speed's speculations concerning telegraph science.
        Speed, J.J.; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Hicks, Charles C.; Allen, Oliver E.
      - May 19, 1849 - June 4, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 13)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, western lines, stock subscriptions, conflict with O'Reilly's lines, Canadian lines.
        May 19, 1849. J.J. Speed to Ezra Cornell:
        "?our operators here had been supoened to give evidence in relation to private business sent over the line."
        May 28, 1849. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "?as I have got Fall Creek, I shall have to stay at home and attend to it, and you will have to become Captain General of the lightning."
        June 6, 1849. Ezra Cornell to D.T. Tillotson:
        "?after talking with O'Reilly a short time, Mann said he became convinced that they wished him to engage in a swindling operation to fleece his neighbours & friends?"
        Milwaukee; Ithaca; Indiana; Ohio.
        Speed, J.J.; Jackson, Tower; Lee, John J.S.
      - June 5, 1849 - June 20, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 14)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, stock subscriptions, western lines, conflict with O'Reilly's lines.
        Connecticut; Ohio.
        Speed, J.J.; Beebe, Jeremiah S.
      - June 23, 1849 - July 2, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, stock subscriptions, Cleveland & Cincinnati line, New-York & Erie line, St. Louis line, O'Reilly conflict, finances; Ithaca & Auburn Telegraph Company.
        June 30, 1849. Samuel F.B. Morse to Ezra Cornell:
        "If you have suffered from the outrageous rascalities of the O'Reilly pirates in any degree, I have suffered tenfold more, but there will soon be an end of their machinations if there is any force in law or justice."
        Cleveland; Milan, Ohio; Ithaca.
        Wade, J.H.; Speed, J.J.; Allen, Oliver E.; Tillotson, D.T.; Spencer, D.D.; Bristol, John S.; Morse, Samuel F.B.
      - July 4, 1849 - July 12, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        Telegraph business correspondence: Connecticut & Vermont line, proposed lines, stock subscriptions, materials and supplies, new western lines; Ithaca & Auburn Telegraph Company.
        July 4, 1849. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "?Ithaca has a plank road from Hotel to Inlet, one mile, great for Tompkins Company ? a dozen has been planed ? but have all evaporated in a few set speaches at public meetings ? but our Ithaca plank road makes a fine track for the 4th of Julyers to try their nags on."
        Also Ezra Cornell's experiments with line connections.
        Ithaca; Detroit.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Tillotson, D.T.; Bristol, John S.; Faxton, Theodore; McGowan, S.W.; Speed, J.J.; Hotchkiss, S.W.; Beebe, Jeremiah S.
      - July 13, 1849 - July 26, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, stock subscriptions, materials and supplies, new lines.
        July 13, 1849. J.J. Speed in Detroit to Ezra Cornell:
        "You have warned me in the past to avoid experiments: but I am making one more. I have got a Mrs. Sheldon to take the office at Jackson and am going to get your sister Mrs. Wood to take the Albion office: both are abundantly qualified to do the business better than any boy, or man, that we can afford to pay in those places. If the ex works as well as I have every confidence to believe it will, I will put a woman in the offices at Ann Arbor, Marshall, & Battle Creek?."
        July 15, 1849. Alonzo B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell explaining the working of a telegraph line.
        July 20, 1849. S.W. McGowan to Ezra Cornell discussing possible new lines in northern New York and difficulties in selling subscriptions.
        Detroit; Cleveland; Ithaca.
        Speed, J.J.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Wood, M.L.; Tillotson, D.T.; Faxton, Theodore; Bristol, John S.; McGowan, S.W.; Jackson, Tower.
      - July 27, 1849 - August 9, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 4)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, new lines in Ithaca area (Waterloo, Seneca Falls, Aurora), reconstruction of Ithaca & Elmira line, stock subscriptions, finances.
        July 29, 1849. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell concerning travel between New York and Ithaca, telegraph line operations, Ithaca & Owego railroad, Sodus Canal, and purchase of Fall Creek property:
        "I think after this year I shall give up the Telegraph business to you and Col. Speed and I will turn my attention to the improvement of the property."
        August 6, 1849. J.J. Speed in Detroit describing the effect of the cholera epidemic in the west (mid-west), progress on the Pittsburgh, St. Louis and Cincinnati lines, and finances.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Speed, J.J.; Kendall, Amos; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Tillotson, D.T.; Jackson, Tower.
      - August 11, 1849 - August 23, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        Telegraph business correspondence: Ithaca & Elmira line, New-York & Erie line, Connecticut & Vermont line, stock subscriptions, materials and supplies, finances.
        August 21, 1849. J. H. Wade in Milan to Ezra Cornell reporting on the progress of the Cleveland & Cincinnati line, and the effect of cholera in the region.
        August 21, 1849. S.W. Hotchkiss in Galena to Ezra Cornell reporting on progress of new lines in Illinois and Wisconsin and the O'Reilly conflict.
        Ithaca; Cleveland; Galena, Ill.
        Bush, I.L.; Tillotson, D.T.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Lewis, A.S.; Wade, J.H.; Hotchkiss, S.W.; Speed, J.J.
      - August 25, 1849 - September 10, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, Connecticut & Vermont line, finances, Ithaca & Elmira line, Albany & Newburgh line.
        August 25, 1849. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "You have a young brother here about 3 days old. He is a fine fellow and will soon want a situation in a Telegraph office."
        September 8, 1849. Theodore S. Faxton to Ezra Cornell concerning settlement of Ezra Cornell's accounts with the New York, Albany & Buffalo Telegraph Company.
        September 10, 1849. S.W. Hotchkiss to Ezra Cornell from Sheboygan concerning new lines under construction in the west, competition from O'Reilly, and the effects of the cholera epidemic.
        Ithaca; Connecticut; Buffalo.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Smith, F.O.J.; Bush, I.L.; Lewis, A.S.; Tillotson, D.T.; Dewey, Theodore; Speed, J.J.; Faxton, Theodore; Hotchkiss, S.W.
      - September 11, 1849 - September 19, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, New-York & Erie line, finances, Connecticut & Vermont line.
        September 17, 1849. J.J. Speed to Ezra Cornell, diagrams and description of new "switch" he had developed which would allow transmitting of messages over long distances without rewriting (connecting circuits). 2nd letter, same date, concerns progress on new western lines (Cleveland & Cincinnati, St. Louis).
        Mt. Vernon, Ohio.
        Speed, J.J.; Tillotson, D.T.; Boardman, Douglass; Allen, T.F.; French, B.B.
      - September 20, 1849 - October 4, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 8)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, new western lines (Zanesville, St. Louis), finances; Connecticut & Vermont Telegraph Company; railroad convention in St. Louis.
        September 20, 1849. Beach Brothers to Ezra Cornell inquiring as to arrangements for transmission of news messages for The New York Sun over the New-York & Erie and the Erie & Michigan lines. (Letter of October 1, 1849 indicates this idea has been abandoned by the Beach Brothers)
        September 20, 1849. J.J. Speed to Ezra Cornell concerning prospects looking good for new western lines, O'Reilly conflict, and connecting circuits.
        September 23, 1849. Phebe Wood to Ezra Cornell:
        "I think that I shall like tellegraphing if I have good instruments. I wish you would come and see us. I could now appreciate some instructions in regard to electricity."
        Speed, J.J.; Wood, Phebe; Smith, F.O.J.; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Tillotson, D.T.; Wade, J.H.
      - October 5, 1849 - October 18, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, New-York & Erie line, Cleveland & Cincinnati line, office operations.
        October 1849. George B. Prescott's answer to the bill of complaint by Ezra Cornell.
        October 7, 1849. J.J. Speed to Ezra Cornell, regarding Speed's new circuit connector:
        "You say work the telegraph as it is, and not allow myself to chase Jack-O-Lanterns. I answer yes, if I cannot make the public believe that my Jack-O-Lantern is a real bonafide lighthouse - and induce them to pay me their money to help build it."
        October 9, 1849. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell reprimanding him for closing his telegraph office early on an election night:
        "This will not do and if it cant be reformed we will have some turnouts."
        Cleveland.
        Speed, J.J.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Benedict, E.D.; Wade, J.H.; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Wheeler, M.; Allen, T.F.; Jackson, Tower.
      - October 20, 1849 - October 31, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        Telegraph business correspondence: Cleveland & Cincinnati line, finances, materials and supplies (brimstone insulators), Wisconsin lines, New-York & Erie line.
        October 20, 1849. D.T. Tillotson to Ezra Cornell reporting on survey of Chenango Valley. October 20, 1849. E.D Benedict to operators connected with Cleveland and Pittsburgh line detailing a
        "system of doing business in regular order, and promptly, at the same time giving each and every office a fair and equal chance."
        October 27, 1849. J.J. Speed to Ezra Cornell describing continued experiments with his switch.
        October 29, 1849. Ezra Cornell to D.T. Tillotson discussing Ithaca area lines (Waterloo and Elmira), operations of House line and Bain telegraph lines in the east, and the business of the New-York & Erie line.
        Ithaca; Zanesville, Ohio; Milwaukee; New York City.
        Tillotson, D.T.; Benedict, E.D.; Speed, J.J.; Hotchkiss, S.W.; Smith, F.O.J.; Jackson, G.J.
      - November 1, 1849 - November 26, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 11)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, Erie & Michigan line, Cleveland & Cincinnati line; Ohio lines; death of Elizabeth Cornell.
        November 4, 1849. E.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell discussing the potential of the Cincinnati, Wheeling, & Pittsburgh line and his view of Speed's switch as an important improvement in telegraph operations.
        November 15, 1849. Letters of condolence from H.C. Buell and W.W. Marks to Alonzo B. Cornell on the death of his sister Elizabeth.
        November 24, 1849. Phebe Wood to Ezra Cornell, expressing sympathy on Elizabeth's death and discussing the success of women telegraph operators:
        "John writes me that Jane intends going to learn the tailors trade but I think she would do better to learn to telegraph. I hear that they employ ladies in ops east."
        Ithaca; Cleveland; Albion.
        Jackson, G.J.; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Cornell, E.B.; Speed, J.J.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Bristol, John S.; Cornell, Elizabeth; Wood, Phebe.
      - November 27, 1849 - December 12, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, materials and supplies, office operations, New-York & Erie line, stock subscriptions.
        Tillotson, D.T.; Cornell, E.B.; Chace, Thomas; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Speed, J.J.; Wade, J.H.
      - December 15, 1849 - December 26, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 13)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, new lines (Ohio, Wheeling to New Philadelphia), Zanesville line, office operations, materials and supplies.
        December 18, 1849. J.J. Speed to Ezra Cornell discussing finances, results of his work in Ohio, and future plans for lines to the west.
        December 22, 1849. Ezra Cornell to Board of Directors of Hudson River Railroad Company proposing a reciprocal arrangement for the right to erect poles along the railroad line from New York to Poughkeepsie and for free passage of his men in return for telegraph services for railroad business.
        December 25, 1849. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann and children, from Peekskill:
        "I wish you all a Merry Christmas, a Merry, Merry Christmas, and I hope old Santa Claus wont be so verry busy as to pass by?without even droping in to catch a glance of those bewitching merry eyes, of my darling Mary or the cherub smiles of my baby Boy?."
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Speed, J.J.; O'Reilly, Henry; Haviland, J.; Dunham, J.
      - 14 December 27, 1849 - January 14, 1850 (Box 10, Folder 14)
        Telegraph business correspondence: stock subscriptions, finances, Zanesville line, Zanesville & Wheeling-Pittsburgh line, Ithaca area lines (Auburn, Palmyra); New-York & Erie Telegraph Association.
        January 5, 1850. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "We miss our dear Elizabeth verry much from our family circle our recollections of her innocent mirth, and cheerful good nature with hopes for her eternal happiness is our only consolation - and her sudden departure should admonish us all to be ready for a like event, and may we all in the end meet her in happiness."
        Cleveland; Ithaca.
        Speed, J.J.; Tillotson, D.T.; Jackson, Tower; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Boardman, Douglass; Eddy, J.
      - January 15, 1850 - January 29, 1850 (Box 10, Folder 15)
        Telegraph business correspondence: stock subscriptions, office operations, finances, materials and supplies; New York & Erie Telegraph Association.
        January 28, 1850. T.W. Hotchkiss to Ezra Cornell from Milwaukee concerning finances, progress on Wisconsin lines, and the pirates.
        January 29, 1850. T. F. Allen to Ezra Cornell giving account of his attempts to raise subscriptions for a line from Towanda to Owego.
        Cleveland; Milwaukee.
        Wood, M.L.; Brown, Charles L.; Tillotson, D.T.; Luther, G.; Morrell, John J.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Hotchkiss, S.W.; Smith, F.O.J.; Wood, O.S.
      - January 30, 1850 - February 19, 1850 (Box 10, Folder 16)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, stock subscriptions; New-York & Erie Telegraph Association.
        February 25 and 29, 1850. Proposition by Ezra Cornell to New York and Erie Railroad Company.
        Cleveland; Peekskill, N.Y.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Wade, J.H.; Northrop, C.C.; Tillotson, D.T.
      - March 1, 1850 - March 29, 1850 (Box 11, Folder 1)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, patent rights, stocks, finances; New-York & Erie Telegraph Association.
        Ohio; New York City; Ithaca.
        Mowrey, LeRoy; Tillotson, D.T.; Cornell, E.B.
      - March 30, 1850 - April 15, 1850 (Box 11, Folder 2)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, patent disputes, stocks, finances; Magnetic Telegraph Company.
        Smith, F.O.J.; Speed, J.J.; Morse, Samuel F.B.
      - April 16, 1850 - May 8, 1850 (Box 11, Folder 3)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, patent disputes, stocks, finances.
        April 20, 1850. Alonzo B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "I am very sorry to hear that you are so strained in your money matters. Though it is not very much to be wondered at considering from whence you expect money."
        April 1850. Letters from Speed describing possible improvements to telegraph technology, and a method of preventing steam boilers from exploding.
        Detroit; Ithaca.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Speed, J.J.
      - May 9, 1850 - May 22, 1850 (Box 11, Folder 4)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances.
        May 18, 1850. Statement describing the operations of the New York telegraph station, including transcriptions of messages and comment on illicit use of the line.
        Speed, J.J.; Wood, M.L.
      - May 25, 1850 - June 11, 1850 (Box 11, Folder 5)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, New York City operations, Erie & Michigan line.
        May 27, 1850. Letter from Speed describing possible improvements to telegraph technology.
        Ithaca; New York City; Fredonia.
        Tyler, A.L.; Robinson, Charles B.; Speed, J.J.; Beebe, Jeremiah S.
      - June 12, 1850 - July 4, 1850 (Box 11, Folder 6)
        Telegraph business correspondence: materials and supplies, finances, New York City operations, stocks.
        Robinson, Charles B.; Kendall, Amos; Smith, F.O.J.; Bagley, B.; Speed, J.J.
      - July 5, 1850 - July 19, 1850 (Box 11, Folder 7)